This material is made available to you by or on
NOTE CONF
behalf of the University of Melbourne under section 113P of
the Copyright Act 1968.
NOTE CONF
It may be subject to copyright.
For more information, visit the university copyright website.
NOTE CONF
OK Good morning.
Um, I expect to get fewer people tending because today
NOTE CONF
is, uh, this week is assessment week.
And experience tells me that during assessment weeks, Attendance in
NOTE CONF
lectures usually drops significantly.
Well, we still have 50 students out of 210, roughly
NOTE CONF
25%, which isn't too bad.
I hope that you're getting something out of attending the
NOTE CONF
lecture.
In person.
NOTE CONF
Especially nowadays everything is recorded and it's just easier to
sit home and watch it.
NOTE CONF
While doing a few other things.
Um So this week we're talking about technological controls, but
NOTE CONF
we're going to do it in a Strategic sense.
So the aim is not to focus on the technical
NOTE CONF
aspects of the technological controls, but the strategic aspects of
technological controls, which is In what circumstances would you deploy
NOTE CONF
a particular control?
Right.
NOTE CONF
What is the control for?
How does it allow you to or enable you to
NOTE CONF
reach or achieve your strategic purposes?
So, we're gonna use A castle, medieval castle as a,
NOTE CONF
a framework or an, an architecture to explain How to
categorize controls and where to put them.
NOTE CONF
And so today's objective is to do exactly that, which
is to introduce some technological controls and to explain how
NOTE CONF
they get used in the strategic picture.
So, studying module 5, of course, uh, there is quite
NOTE CONF
a bit of reading.
Why are my page numbers the wrong way?
NOTE CONF
I don't know to go back and fix that.
Sorry.
NOTE CONF
It's a lot of pages.
Yes.
NOTE CONF
Well, um, we are not going to ask you to,
we're not going to test you on the content of
NOTE CONF
those 88 pages outside of what's in this lecture.
So the idea is don't hit the textbook yet, go
NOTE CONF
through the lecture, understand what we're after, and then Pick
from the textbook the parts that you need in order
NOTE CONF
to help you to understand what we're saying in the
lecture, OK?
NOTE CONF
So don't read the textbook pages, all of the 88
pages, uh, word for word.
NOTE CONF
You can, we stop here.
It's good for your general knowledge, but we're not going
NOTE CONF
to test you on the intricacies of the technical, you
know, the technologies.
NOTE CONF
What we want you to do is to understand the
technologies insofar as they support the strategy, so you can
NOTE CONF
decide how little or how much you need to read
in order to get you to that point.
NOTE CONF
So the textbook is background reading to support, not primary
reading for examination.
NOTE CONF
This is generally true, by the way, for most of
the weeks, but especially true for this week.
NOTE CONF
So, study the Canvas module, read the textbook, and so
as much as it will support you.
NOTE CONF
Uh, discussion questions on Canvas, attend the workshop.
In the workshop this week is going to be presentations
NOTE CONF
for the whole 2 hours, uh, and maybe even for
the next week.
NOTE CONF
So I suspect, depending on which workshop you're in, you
will not get a chance to speak about the actual
NOTE CONF
content with your tutor in this week, but the tutors
will catch up.
NOTE CONF
In a following week.
So, oral presentations.
NOTE CONF
If there's time, there'll be Q&A.
If there's time, there'll be the teaching case.
NOTE CONF
So two main learning objectives, defense and depth, which is
one of the key.
NOTE CONF
Themes of this week and technological controls.
You should be able to understand what is defense in
NOTE CONF
depth.
You should be able to explore the concept of defense
NOTE CONF
in depth.
You should have the castle model very clearly in your
NOTE CONF
mind.
You should be able to identify the parts of a
NOTE CONF
castle in the physical world and explain what role they
play.
NOTE CONF
And then in the digital environment you should be able
to overlay.
NOTE CONF
Digital controls on the castle to be able to explain
how these digital controls achieve strategic objectives.
NOTE CONF
Going back to the triplet model.
You should now know this really, really.
NOTE CONF
You should know this well, um.
The asset is what we're protecting.
NOTE CONF
The threat is the actor that is trying to reduce
the value of the asset.
NOTE CONF
Every combination of asset, threat and vulnerability creates a scenario,
a unique scenario.
NOTE CONF
Those unique scenarios collectively constitute your risk exposure, and your
security is designed to reduce your risk exposure, and it
NOTE CONF
does that by applying.
A range of controls.
NOTE CONF
These can be administrative controls, managerial controls, technological controls, etc.
behavioral controls, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
We're talking this week now for the first time we're
NOTE CONF
going to start to dig deep into a particular category
of controls, and we're going to start with technological controls.
NOTE CONF
And in order to understand technological controls, we're going to
take a non-technological example, something physical, something concrete, something we
NOTE CONF
can all identify with, and something that puts together a
story or a or actually operates on an existing mental
NOTE CONF
model that you already have.
Everybody knows what a castle looks like.
NOTE CONF
Everybody's seen the movie where a castle has been the,
you know, the main.
NOTE CONF
The main setting So whether you have deliberately desired to
or not, you have learned a lot about castles, and
NOTE CONF
we're going to tap into that existing mental model and
maybe dig a little bit deeper.
NOTE CONF
And then we're going to explain how this has to
do with technological controls.
NOTE CONF
So, I don't know why somebody's struggling with the door.
Oh, he is struggling with the door because pushing the
NOTE CONF
wrong way.
OK.
NOTE CONF
So, um, Once upon a time, thousands of years ago.
When an army invades a territory and conquers the territory,
NOTE CONF
um, generals, leaders, kings found out very quickly that it's
easy to conquer new territory.
NOTE CONF
It's hard to keep the territory.
So you can't keep a standing army, hundreds of thousands
NOTE CONF
of soldiers, and feed them and keep them fed and
taken care of just to control a piece of land.
NOTE CONF
You can use them to invade and to conquer and
to acquire the prize, but once you've acquired it, how
NOTE CONF
do you keep it?
The issue here now is in order to keep it,
NOTE CONF
you have to have some presence on the land.
It can't be as big as an army.
NOTE CONF
It's got to be a very small army, a small
garrison.
NOTE CONF
But the issue is a small army or a small
number of people that are holding the land are easily.
NOTE CONF
Conquered by another invading large army.
So you can't keep the land.
NOTE CONF
So what do we do, right?
We need to find a way to Level the playing
NOTE CONF
field between a small army that's designed to hold the
land and a large army that's invading, and what they
NOTE CONF
designed was a castle.
A castle is an asymmetric construct, an asymmetric mechanism by
NOTE CONF
which a small group of people can leverage can be
leveraged to defend against a very large group of people.
NOTE CONF
So instead of 1 to 1, we're talking about one
to many.
NOTE CONF
Now how is the castle able to do this?
Well, it's taken hundreds of years to refine the strategy
NOTE CONF
and the architecture and the engineering behind castles, so we're
going to take a look at the best of the
NOTE CONF
castles rather than the most, not the most primitive, but
the most advanced.
NOTE CONF
So starting point, you always build a castle on the
highest point in the land.
NOTE CONF
So if you've got a mountainous territory, you choose the
top of the mountain to build your castle.
NOTE CONF
Why?
Because it's hard to get to.
NOTE CONF
In order to conquer the castle, an army has to
actually get to the castle, which means traveling upwards on
NOTE CONF
a mountain, which is very difficult to do.
Second of all, if you are on top of a
NOTE CONF
mountain and you are living in a castle, you can
see an invading army coming days away, which gives you
NOTE CONF
lots of time to prepare.
If you were at the bottom of a valley, you
NOTE CONF
would not know until the army is almost on top
of you and you have no forewarning.
NOTE CONF
So.
Being on top of a mountain gives you surveillance, gives
NOTE CONF
you the distance, and it gives you an easier terrain
to defend.
NOTE CONF
So you fight downwards as an army that's invading fights
upwards.
NOTE CONF
Gravity is on your side, so if you have archers
and they're firing off arrows, they go a lot further
NOTE CONF
if they're coming from the top of the mountain than
if they're coming from the bottom of the mountain.
NOTE CONF
So there are a lot of advantages in setting the
castle at the top of the mountain.
NOTE CONF
But that's just the beginning.
The location is just the beginning.
NOTE CONF
Then come all the features of the castle.
So you build a moat around the castle.
NOTE CONF
You dig a deep, deep, deep trench all the way
around the castle if you can, and you fill it
NOTE CONF
with water so that horses can't jump over it.
That will slow down an invading army to a standstill
NOTE CONF
while they try to fill the boat and try to
cross it.
NOTE CONF
Then, as you can see in this image, there are
lots of individual features of the building itself.
NOTE CONF
There is the fact that the passages are winding.
And the passages are narrow, which means a small army
NOTE CONF
on the inside can block.
The approach to the castle and fight in small groups
NOTE CONF
which really negates the advantage of the invading army because
of their I mean they can't use their large numbers
NOTE CONF
to put pressure or to rush you or to surround
you and they have to fight in small groups which
NOTE CONF
gives you the ability to delay the invading army's approach
to you or their acquisition of the asset.
NOTE CONF
And really sophisticated castles are concentric, so there's a castle
within a castle within a castle, so a retreating garrison
NOTE CONF
can just simply, even if the outer walls are breached,
they can lock themselves in an inner castle, and then
NOTE CONF
the invading army has to breach that inner castle, and
they keep locking themselves in inner castles until you get
NOTE CONF
to the keep or wherever these crown jewels or assets
are.
NOTE CONF
And of course along the way there's lots of additional
traps.
NOTE CONF
Uh, you know, surprises that the invading army will, will
face, and the castle is engineered in a way.
NOTE CONF
That it's got winding passages so you can't put pressure.
You have to do quick turns.
NOTE CONF
You've got staircases that are winding as well, so if
you're going up a staircase, then you can't use your
NOTE CONF
right arm to fight, whereas the descending person you're fighting
has a free right arm to fight.
NOTE CONF
All of these are very, very carefully engineered.
The end product of this is that a small group
NOTE CONF
of people in a castle withstand a very large army.
That's the asymmetry of it.
NOTE CONF
And within the castle are all these controls.
There are lots of them that are working together.
NOTE CONF
There's the guards and the archers and the surveillance and
the passages and everything, right?
NOTE CONF
So there's a whole range of things.
Now, here is.
NOTE CONF
The same castle Much more sophisticated design, but we can
now see on the left hand side, I don't know
NOTE CONF
if you can read, unfortunately, you can't because the cameras
here are really small.
NOTE CONF
Um, but you've got on the left hand side, all
the physical features, and then on the right hand side,
NOTE CONF
you have, you can actually overlay digital features on this.
So for instance, what is the You've got the perimeter
NOTE CONF
wall of a castle.
What is the closest digital technology to a perimeter wall?
NOTE CONF
How do you enforce a perimeter around your organization in
the digital environment?
NOTE CONF
What is the equivalent of a Perimeter wall in the
digital environment.
NOTE CONF
No, so we said, sorry?
A firewall.
NOTE CONF
So a firewall, not really a wall, but In the
digital environment, unlike in the physical environment, there's no concept
NOTE CONF
of land, right?
There is no land.
NOTE CONF
So in the physical world, land has been set up
for us, right?
NOTE CONF
We didn't construct the land, we didn't engineer the land,
we just, the land is there.
NOTE CONF
So in order to create separation, and this is an
important thing, right, the fundamental, the fundamental strategy in security
NOTE CONF
when you've got an asset and a threat.
And you want to put in a control is to
NOTE CONF
separate the asset from the threat.
You have to create a separation and you have to
NOTE CONF
enforce that boundary.
That's how you create security by separating assets from threats.
NOTE CONF
So separation on a flat piece of land looks like
a wall that goes around an asset.
NOTE CONF
Right, you put the asset in the center, you build
a wall around the asset, and now you've separated the
NOTE CONF
asset from the threat.
In the digital environment, there's no land, but there are
NOTE CONF
IP addresses, and IP addresses can contact other IP addresses
and traffic can flow between them.
NOTE CONF
So there's no land, but if I could control traffic
moving from one IP address to another IP address by
NOTE CONF
putting a filter.
A firewall.
NOTE CONF
I essentially have a wall, a perimeter wall.
Yeah, it's essentially, you'll have to think about it, but
NOTE CONF
it's essentially the same thing.
So a firewall sits between, sits on the traffic and
NOTE CONF
it filters traffic.
We'll talk about it in detail in a moment, but
NOTE CONF
it's an example of how you create a boundary.
The boundary has to be enforced on the traffic, and
NOTE CONF
that's what creates the wall.
So you see here, you've got these concentric castles can
NOTE CONF
be created by having an internet connection that goes into
an organization, connects thousands of terminals, and you create subgroups
NOTE CONF
of these terminals by using multiple firewalls in series to
create essentially concentric castles.
NOTE CONF
If I put my most valuable document behind the last
firewall in a series of 2 to 3 firewalls, then
NOTE CONF
you have to actually break through firewall number 1, then
firewall 23 to get to the document, and that is
NOTE CONF
the same as breaking through castle 1, castle 2, castle
3 to get to the king.
NOTE CONF
Do you see the parallel?
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
So in the olden days, 20, you know, up until
recently, all organizations, their digital environments were structured like castles.
NOTE CONF
And what was creating the castle environment was firewalls, right?
Trying to actually segregate or compartmentalize digital terminals, assets from
NOTE CONF
other assets, right?
Using firewalls as pinching mechanisms or filtering mechanisms to segment
NOTE CONF
traffic.
So if you can segment traffic, you're essentially creating a
NOTE CONF
castle.
We're going to go through, so I want you to
NOTE CONF
keep in your mind, this castle architecture because as we
go through the slides today, we're going to look at
NOTE CONF
the different digital technologies that allow this castle, the castle
environment to exist.
NOTE CONF
So, first line of defense is always separation.
Just like in the castle where you've got outer walls,
NOTE CONF
you've got a moat, you want to separate the invading
army from the actual asset.
NOTE CONF
The first line of defense is your ability to separate.
So what is a firewall?
NOTE CONF
It just basically is a filter.
Discriminates against information that's flowing into your organization.
NOTE CONF
It can be a physical device.
It can be a piece of software.
NOTE CONF
It can be a combination of hardware and software, but
it's basically a barrier between What you want to protect
NOTE CONF
and what you don't trust.
So your organization's inner sanctum is your trusted environment and
NOTE CONF
outside the internet and other organizations would be the untrusted
environment.
NOTE CONF
What enforces the boundary between the trusted and the untrusted
environment is essentially your firewall, that kind of device, that
NOTE CONF
kind of mechanism.
This is a very simple diagram from the textbook, a
NOTE CONF
very simple packet filter.
There are there are successive, increasingly sophisticated mechanisms to enforce
NOTE CONF
this boundary, but this is the simplest.
On the left hand side is the internet.
NOTE CONF
On the right hand side is your organization.
In the middle, on the dotted line, the dotted line
NOTE CONF
is your internet traffic or your network traffic, and basically
that device that sits on that traffic line.
NOTE CONF
Filters all the information, looks at the header of all
these packets, and says, Do I want to allow this
NOTE CONF
traffic to come in or do I not?
If I don't, I reject it.
NOTE CONF
If I do, I allow it to go through, and
that's it.
NOTE CONF
At a very simple level, It can just look at
the source and destination of each of these packets and
NOTE CONF
decide if it wants to allow the packet to come
in or not, and just that filtering mechanism creates a
NOTE CONF
boundary, a logical boundary, and that boundary, if enforced consistently.
Creates that protective wall or protective separation, and you don't
NOTE CONF
normally have just one firewall or you don't normally have
just one internet connection.
NOTE CONF
You might have a number of connections to the internet
across your organization and you need to have a boundary
NOTE CONF
across each of them because if you have a boundary
on just one of them, then they'll Be traffic just
NOTE CONF
going around it, right?
That's equivalent to having a castle with walls on one
NOTE CONF
or two sides, but open territory on the other.
Makes no sense at all, right?
NOTE CONF
For the castle to be effective, it's got to have
a boundary that goes all the way around it, and
NOTE CONF
that means for all your internet traffic coming into your
organization, you need to enforce a boundary, which is usually
NOTE CONF
done with a firewall.
There are, the more sophisticated firewalls actually have enforced different
NOTE CONF
addressing schemes.
So the internet may be using TCPIP as a protocol
NOTE CONF
and using an addressing scheme that looks like 192.250250.
blah blah blah, and internally within the organization, you can
NOTE CONF
have a different addressing scheme, like 10.1.1.
whatever, right?
NOTE CONF
And the whole point of having different adversing scheme is
like having different languages.
NOTE CONF
Imagine if everybody on the internet communicated using English and
you inside your organization spoke in French.
NOTE CONF
Any traffic that goes around the firewall is like somebody
who is speaking English trying to speak to somebody who
NOTE CONF
only understands French without a translator.
The firewall acts like the.
NOTE CONF
Translator, it's like a network addressing tool that says, oh,
outside traffic you can come inside, but I'm going to
NOTE CONF
change your address so that you can actually find your
destination.
NOTE CONF
If you find a way around me, you're not, you
can find, you can get onto the network, but you'll
NOTE CONF
never find anything inside because the addressing scheme inside is
a different language to what you can speak.
NOTE CONF
So if you can enforce a translator on the boundary.
Then you can ensure that nobody can get around your
NOTE CONF
firewall, even if somehow internet traffic gets around it.
So there's some pretty sophisticated mechanisms to try to enforce
NOTE CONF
that boundary.
That is the bottom line.
NOTE CONF
But if we create a boundary, how do we get
authorized individuals to get through it?
NOTE CONF
Again, if you have a castle and you pulled your
drawbridge, nobody's going to get in until you put your
NOTE CONF
drawbridge down and people walk through.
Well, in the digital world, we have a drawbridge as
NOTE CONF
well that we can pull down and it's called a
VPN, right, a virtual private network, and it's really quite
NOTE CONF
simple.
The VPN is like a gate.
NOTE CONF
It can be opened.
It can allow you to come in.
NOTE CONF
I'm sure you've used a VPN before, right?
A piece of software, you have a username or password
NOTE CONF
to allow you to log in to a remote device,
gives you credentials, and you basically then acquire an addressing,
NOTE CONF
an address that allows you to navigate a, a domain
that you would not otherwise be able to get into.
NOTE CONF
So if I'm an organization and I have, you know,
assets like special documents, services like printers, etc.
NOTE CONF
and you work in my organization, but you say, hey,
I need to go overseas, and I still need to
NOTE CONF
work on these documents.
How am I going to do that?
NOTE CONF
Well, we can give you VPN software and you can
log in.
NOTE CONF
And it'll be as if you're inside the organization, but
actually physically you're outside.
NOTE CONF
All that means is there's an envelope, you know, a
logical envelope around you that allows you to enter or
NOTE CONF
to cross that boundary, and we just given your addressing
scheme, we just think of you as your inside, even
NOTE CONF
though physically you're outside.
So you can see the mechanism here, teleworker, you know,
NOTE CONF
request internet connection.
Uses a piece of software.
NOTE CONF
That software then envelopes the traffic from that teleworker in
a special encrypted packet which travels across the internet, which
NOTE CONF
is untrusted territory, gets dropped, gets the packet gets taken
out, and then the traffic gets dropped inside the organization,
NOTE CONF
and it's as if that person was inside all along.
So that is the first line of defense.
NOTE CONF
It's the boundary, and then we deal with how to
cross the boundary if you're authorized.
NOTE CONF
So unauthorized people, here's the boundary you cannot cross.
Authorized people, you can cross the boundary, we'll give you
NOTE CONF
special privileges to do that.
So, up until now, we've just explained how to compartmentalize,
NOTE CONF
how to create compartments, how to create separation, how to
take a piece of land and to break it up
NOTE CONF
into pieces, right?
Maybe something I, I, I should probably say is The
NOTE CONF
whole reason why you set up a castle isn't just
to deny the invader from getting access to your asset.
NOTE CONF
It's actually to delay the invader because the right way
to think about it is the invader will ultimately get
NOTE CONF
to the asset because it will ultimately break through those
barriers.
NOTE CONF
So the aim, you can't expect that you'll be able
to deny them completely.
NOTE CONF
You can, however, expect that you will delay them.
That's predictable and consistent.
NOTE CONF
So what's my strategy if I am relying entirely on
a delay?
NOTE CONF
The strategy is that no castle sits in isolation.
There's always a network of castles, each castle 50 kilometers,
NOTE CONF
100 kilometers from each other.
And so if you can delay the invader long enough,
NOTE CONF
help will come from the nearby castle, and that help
will be in the form of an army, and that
NOTE CONF
army will sandwich the invader between your castle walls and
the army behind them.
NOTE CONF
That is the ultimate strategy.
So in the digital environment, this strategy is the digital
NOTE CONF
space that you have in your organization can be compartmentalized,
and if somebody attacks your organization and they get into
NOTE CONF
a certain segment or part of it, they shouldn't be
able to get into all of the organization, right?
NOTE CONF
So each compartment slows down the attacker from getting to
another compartment.
NOTE CONF
OK, that's why you Break up your organization structurally into
compartments which are enforced by firewalls, and each compartment presents
NOTE CONF
another challenge.
Of course you can increase the challenge by buying firewalls
NOTE CONF
from different vendors to ensure that just because they can
break through one boundary doesn't mean they understand how to
NOTE CONF
break through the next boundary.
The same vendor is not a good idea.
NOTE CONF
Multiple vendors raises the bar for the attacker.
OK, so that's the boundary part.
NOTE CONF
The second part is observation.
So in a castle, you have castle guards who are
NOTE CONF
surveilling the environment, because not all attacks look like an
army.
NOTE CONF
It could be somebody who's dressed in plain clothes, somebody
who smuggles themselves pretending to be somebody else, and come
NOTE CONF
into the castle and then open the castle gates for
somebody, for another group of people coming in, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
The point is, what does good traffic.
NOTE CONF
And bad traffic look like inside a castle, that is
usually enforced by castle guards, right, whose job it is
NOTE CONF
to watch people move in crowds and to see which
crowds look like they are benign and which ones are
NOTE CONF
not.
We have the same sort of thing called intrusion detection
NOTE CONF
systems.
Idea systems are basically computer programs.
NOTE CONF
They are a second line of defense.
They watch traffic on the network and they try to
NOTE CONF
decide if the traffic is problematic or not.
And if it is problematic, they'll send an alert to
NOTE CONF
an administrator saying look at this, look at that, or
maybe if they're an intrusion detection and prevention system, they
NOTE CONF
may shut down the network.
As soon as they detect a certain type of malicious
NOTE CONF
traffic.
But the idea is they're primary, primarily there to observe.
NOTE CONF
And in the olden days of IDF systems, In the
olden days of idea systems.
NOTE CONF
They used to just look at databases of signatures, so
bad traffic had a signature, and so a database of
NOTE CONF
signatures was all the ID system had to go on,
looking at the traffic, trying constantly to match the traffic
NOTE CONF
against the database to see if it matched.
If it matched, then it's malicious.
NOTE CONF
If it doesn't match, it's not very primitive, but that's
what they used to use.
NOTE CONF
Of course, as time went on, anomaly detection became the
norm, trying to figure out what is normal traffic by
NOTE CONF
collecting statistics, empirical data about the traffic to establish what
is normality and then to use that as a way
NOTE CONF
to identify what is abnormal and then to find or
to at least suspect that traffic and to raise an
NOTE CONF
alarm so that somebody, a human, can look at it
and decide if it is anomalous or not.
NOTE CONF
I mean, anomaly detection and signature detection have been there
for a while, but with AI and machine learning and
NOTE CONF
all these new tools, being able to develop more sophisticated
definitions of what's normal is possible.
NOTE CONF
And that was always the issue with observation.
One, a lot of the traffic is encrypted.
NOTE CONF
Number 2, what's normal?
It's impossible to tell what's normal because all the traffic
NOTE CONF
is so varied.
People do weird things all the time.
NOTE CONF
How do I decide whether what they're doing is normal
or not?
NOTE CONF
And so anomaly detection never really got anywhere because anomalies,
I mean I remember in 1995.
NOTE CONF
In the computer science department we were playing with an
anomaly detection system.
NOTE CONF
We actually had a neural network based system which basically
said, hey, we can, if we collect data on your
NOTE CONF
rhythm of typing on your keyboard and which applications you
open up when you log in and when you open
NOTE CONF
them up and what you do in those applications, etc.
etc.
NOTE CONF
we collect all that data and we run it through
a neural network, you know, system which is like a
NOTE CONF
It's a very powerful mathematical algorithm that has the ability
to forget, right?
NOTE CONF
Forget is good because people change and, and the algorithm
would learn your behavior and then would forget your old
NOTE CONF
behavior, so it would always be current.
And by doing that, it could set up an alarm
NOTE CONF
to say, hey, student X is logged in as student
X, but that Looks like the rhythm of student Y
NOTE CONF
typing.
That's not student X, that's student Y using student X's
NOTE CONF
account, right?
So that was a really powerful tool, but again, in
NOTE CONF
those days, it was very difficult to establish people's signatures
because people vary so much, their behavior changes depending on
NOTE CONF
what assignments they're doing, what subjects they're doing, blah, blah,
blah, very, very hard to do.
NOTE CONF
So when it comes to observation, one of the key
things is where do you observe from, and on a
NOTE CONF
network there are so many different points that you can
observe traffic from which lead you to different conclusions.
NOTE CONF
So for example, you'll see at location 2, which sits
outside your organization, you see traffic coming into your organization,
NOTE CONF
and location 1 is traffic that passes your firewall.
And if you compare location 2 to location 1, you
NOTE CONF
can figure out whether your firewall is working or not.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
Can you see that?
If you collect traffic at location 2 and location 1
NOTE CONF
and you compare the two, you can tell whether your
firewall rules are working or not.
NOTE CONF
But even if you were to do that and see
all the traffic at that level, so most of the
NOTE CONF
traffic is coming to location 2, coming into your organization,
the content is probably encrypted.
NOTE CONF
So you can see the traffic, you can see the
pattern of traffic, you can see the source destination address,
NOTE CONF
but the contents of the body of it is encrypted.
So where does it get decrypted?
NOTE CONF
It gets decrypted probably at location 4.
So you want to have an observer sitting maybe on
NOTE CONF
the computer, where the traffic is going to end up.
Eventually for the computer to understand the traffic, it's the,
NOTE CONF
the encryption has got to be removed.
And that's where you watch the contents of it.
NOTE CONF
That's where you observe it, right?
So there's no one single point that's perfect.
NOTE CONF
You have to have a number of vantage points on
your network in order to get a holistic view of
NOTE CONF
what's going on, right?
The bottom line, observation.
NOTE CONF
is an essential part of your defense in depth.
You had separation, and now you have observation.
NOTE CONF
And the third line of defense is mediation.
Which is OK, we can take our digital environment and
NOTE CONF
break it down into pieces and set up security around
each piece so that it creates a very challenging series
NOTE CONF
of obstacles for an attacker.
We can observe what's happening in each piece so we
NOTE CONF
can tell if the traffic is normal or abnormal and
raise alarms that way, but ultimately we have to give
NOTE CONF
people access.
So, authentication is, are you who you say you are?
NOTE CONF
When you present your credentials, we have to determine if
you are genuine or not.
NOTE CONF
So that's authentication and then authorization is Given you say
you are who you say you are, what are you
NOTE CONF
allowed to do in this environment?
And again, going back 2030 years, maybe 40, 50 years,
NOTE CONF
in the very early days when cybersecurity, when the, well,
when networking didn't exist, when there was no such thing
NOTE CONF
as a network, it was just terminals.
You would put terminals in secure buildings and put a
NOTE CONF
padlock on the building and that was your security, right?
There's no network, so the only way to interact with
NOTE CONF
the digital environment is to walk up to a computer
and use that terminal.
NOTE CONF
That terminal cannot communicate with anything else, so individual terminals
in a locked building is all the security you need.
NOTE CONF
Then when networks became a thing, there was no building
big enough to house the whole network because they were
NOTE CONF
going from city to city.
So then there was this assumption that when you came
NOTE CONF
up to a computer and you presented your credentials, you
could access everything on that computer.
NOTE CONF
If that computer was networked you could access everything on
the entire network.
NOTE CONF
So somebody decided that this isn't right.
You have many.
NOTE CONF
Different types of people getting access to the computer.
Some people should be restricted to only reading documents.
NOTE CONF
Others reading and writing documents.
Others executing programs, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
And not everybody who reads a document should be able
NOTE CONF
to read all documents, etc.
etc.
NOTE CONF
So multi-level access control was created.
And that was then assigned to your identity.
NOTE CONF
You are person X, you have very particular rights, you
can do certain things and you cannot do other things.
NOTE CONF
That control is now embedded into operating systems and networks.
And There is also an acceptance that sometimes the 1st
NOTE CONF
3 things, authentication, authorization, and control fall over, they, they
don't work.
NOTE CONF
So in that case, the asset should always be in
its native state be encrypted.
NOTE CONF
So that if a, if the approach to the asset
doesn't work, you, well, the approach to the asset has
NOTE CONF
to work for it, the encryption to be unlocked, right?
So that's your four level progression in mediation.
NOTE CONF
How do you give people access to the assets that
they need and the services they need?
NOTE CONF
Well, you give them you authenticate them, check who they
are, authorize them, give them certain credentials, control their access.
NOTE CONF
At preferably at the point where they're trying to access
an asset and encrypt the asset or protect the asset
NOTE CONF
in a place where if anything else fails, and the
asset is taken out of its native environment, it's not
NOTE CONF
automatically accessible or usable.
Now, having said all those three things, you can now
NOTE CONF
actually create a castle architecture with those three categories of
controls.
NOTE CONF
You can, if you think about it, you can come
up with a very comprehensive security system or architecture which
NOTE CONF
will create some very challenging environments for an attacker with
those 3 types of controls.
NOTE CONF
But Complex systems and architectures usually have flaws in them.
There will always be something that you forgot, some asset
NOTE CONF
that's public when it should be private, some control that
was some multi-level access control that was set incorrectly, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
So there are certain things that you should do to
NOTE CONF
know what your attack surface is.
What is an attack surface?
NOTE CONF
That is the fully exposed surface of your digital assets.
That's visible to the outside world that can be attacked.
NOTE CONF
And so knowing which systems can be attacked, which ports
are open, what services can be exploited, that is part
NOTE CONF
of your security system, and you do that using Penetration
testers, whose job it is to sit outside the organization
NOTE CONF
and to study the attack surface, and to tell you
which things you thought you had controlled or not controlled,
NOTE CONF
right?
What is the problem with penetration testing?
NOTE CONF
People love penetration testers.
In fact, if you go to most organizations, everything you
NOTE CONF
go, Oh, you've got this problem, ah, penetration testers will
fix it.
NOTE CONF
What is the problem with penetration testing?
It's kind of obvious, isn't it?
NOTE CONF
Yeah, maybe the behavioral aspect is.
Of like human beings Oh yeah, OK, I wasn't thinking
NOTE CONF
about that one, but yeah, yeah, for sure, yeah, yeah.
The the penetration testers are looking at the technology layer
NOTE CONF
and they're not looking at the human layer.
Sure, I wasn't thinking about that one, but yeah, that's
NOTE CONF
a good one.
The main one is that your technology systems are evolving.
NOTE CONF
Your penetration testing is done on day one, and on
day 2, your system doesn't look anything like day 1.
NOTE CONF
So now what's the point of penetration testing, right?
Well, actually it's a bit unfair to say that penetration
NOTE CONF
testing is very useful when you have a long standing
hole or exposure that you're not aware exists.
NOTE CONF
The penetration testers will say, here's an exposure, and you
go, Oh, I thought that was, that was addressed.
NOTE CONF
Very helpful.
But if a penetration tester says, here are the 50
NOTE CONF
problems that you have, and you go, Ah, I fixed
all the 50 problems and I'm secure, guess what?
NOTE CONF
The next week or the next day you just acquired
a new piece of technology and you configured it and
NOTE CONF
you add it to your environment, and now you've got
new holes.
NOTE CONF
So what are you going to do penetration testing every
day?
NOTE CONF
You don't.
Most organizations will do it what, once in 3 months,
NOTE CONF
once in 6 months, once in a year.
If that, So penetration testing is very useful, but in
NOTE CONF
a very, very narrow situation, right?
It's like they take a snapshot of your organization and
NOTE CONF
they give you a snapshot assessment.
You are not a snapshot.
NOTE CONF
You are a living, evolving organization.
Your infrastructure changes maybe even every day.
NOTE CONF
But knowing what is my attack surface, very important.
What system surfaces are exposed, what configurations didn't didn't work,
NOTE CONF
what documents are leaking?
What's on my website that shouldn't be on my website,
NOTE CONF
for instance.
Now, This part is a little bit more harder to
NOTE CONF
understand.
So I need you to really sort of, you know,
NOTE CONF
Yeah, really dig deep here.
The reason why castles, so you know we have something
NOTE CONF
called the cloud.
Yes, everybody's heard of the cloud.
NOTE CONF
Yes, the crowd, yes.
Yes, everybody's heard of the cloud.
NOTE CONF
The cloud is a problem.
Because castles, building a castle around your asset works when
NOTE CONF
you have two things.
Number 1, you own the asset, obviously, but number 2,
NOTE CONF
you possess the asset.
In order to build a castle around your asset, you
NOTE CONF
have to not only own your asset, which you obviously
do, but you have to have possession of the asset.
NOTE CONF
It has to be in your possession.
So if you buy, you know, a digital environment with
NOTE CONF
all these IP addresses inside your organization, you can set
up a castle inside your organization.
NOTE CONF
But the day that you decide that you pick up
your asset and you put it in the cloud, you
NOTE CONF
don't own the territory.
Somebody else owns the land.
NOTE CONF
You cannot build a castle on somebody else's land, in
principle, right?
NOTE CONF
So when you put your asset in somebody else's cloud
like Amazon, AWS, blah blah blah, you don't control the
NOTE CONF
castle, so you cannot build a castle around the asset.
Yeah, you own the asset, but you don't have possession
NOTE CONF
of it.
They have possession of it, and you write a service
NOTE CONF
level agreement to say this is the level of security
that you need to put in place, but you don't
NOTE CONF
have, you don't have the ability to enforce those controls
because it's somebody else's cloud.
NOTE CONF
So, how, what do we do here?
What is, what is going on in the cloud environment?
NOTE CONF
Well, actually, the cloud environment may give you three options.
Number 1, It's called infrastructure as a service where they
NOTE CONF
give you the land.
And you build the castle.
NOTE CONF
Number 2 is platform as a service.
They give you the land and they build the castle,
NOTE CONF
but you have to furnish the castle yourself.
And then the third is software as a service where
NOTE CONF
the land is there, the castle is there, they've furnished
it.
NOTE CONF
All you can do is make rules about how your
asset can be accessed.
NOTE CONF
Do you see the three different things.
Before this, it was our land, our castle, our furnishing,
NOTE CONF
our rules.
When we moved to the cloud, now the land is
NOTE CONF
not ours.
But the question is, The land is not ours.
NOTE CONF
Are they going to build a castle on it and
furnish it and say, OK, you tell us what rules
NOTE CONF
you want to apply, what protocols exist, and we will
enforce them for you.
NOTE CONF
So that is the software as a service, like if
you are in the SAS environment, that's what's happening.
NOTE CONF
They have set up all the infrastructure.
All you can do is tell them what rules you
NOTE CONF
want to have enforced.
That's as much control as they allow you to have.
NOTE CONF
But if you decide, no, I actually want more control,
you can go for a platform as a surface and
NOTE CONF
say, you make the building, but I will design the
rooms and I'll design the rules, and I'll design where
NOTE CONF
my assets get placed.
You just give me an empty building.
NOTE CONF
And then infrastructure service, there's no building.
You have to bring in your developers and create the
NOTE CONF
environment and the rooms and the rules, and then you
can control that, but you don't control the The infrastructure
NOTE CONF
itself, you control.
The, what's happening on the infrastructure.
NOTE CONF
You see the difference between the three things, right?
The 3 different environments, from a security strategy point of
NOTE CONF
view, they're entirely different ball games.
In one, which is the software, the service, you rely
NOTE CONF
on the vendor to manage your security for you.
You only say what the rules are, right?
NOTE CONF
They have to do everything.
And for a lot of organizations like big banks who
NOTE CONF
say, Hey, security is not our problem, you know, this
is not core business, we're happy to go to the
NOTE CONF
cloud, we'll outsource everything.
This is what they're doing.
NOTE CONF
They're giving it to somebody else and they're just trusting
the organization, and their, their castle is going to work.
NOTE CONF
One other aspect is the data itself.
What we want is a situation where we take a
NOTE CONF
data asset and we put it into the cloud or
we take it outside of our environment, which is almost
NOTE CONF
certainly happening today because the workforce is mobile, we want
to be able to lock the data.
NOTE CONF
We want to lock the data.
Allow the data to move around the world in a
NOTE CONF
locked state, but every time somebody tries to access the
data, they refer to the organization and ask us who
NOTE CONF
has access to the, who has the keys, right?
So it's kind of like in a castle, if you
NOTE CONF
had your, your diamonds, your jewels in a strong box
and you locked that box and it was unbreakable, and
NOTE CONF
you gave it to somebody and say, right, you can
go around the world, whatever, it's secure.
NOTE CONF
Nobody's going to open the box without the key, but
we keep the key in the castle.
NOTE CONF
Somebody wants to open the box, they have to come
to the castle and we'll give them the key.
NOTE CONF
And then they can open the box, right?
That's what we want to do with encryption.
NOTE CONF
We want to encrypt our data in a way that
for the for the decryption to happen, they need our
NOTE CONF
permission.
But in order for that to work, you really need
NOTE CONF
an environment where wherever that data travels, there is an
engine or an environment that will keep on checking.
NOTE CONF
Checking with us, taking the keys, opening it up, giving
the, giving access to an identity that's authenticated.
NOTE CONF
So, lastly, I think this is my last slide.
We're seeing.
NOTE CONF
The capsule model has become somewhat outdated.
For most organizations, because I mean the castle as a
NOTE CONF
strategy will never get outdated.
Defense in depth works because if you create boundaries and
NOTE CONF
the boundaries stack up together with all the controls in
those boundaries, the full stack of all those creates this
NOTE CONF
obstacle course and the sum is greater than the parts,
so defense and depth will always work as a strategy.
NOTE CONF
It's just that now we cannot enforce defense in depth
because we don't own the land upon which our assets
NOTE CONF
exist.
They are owned by other people.
NOTE CONF
So you've separated ownership from possession, and now in order
to do that, we have to come up with much
NOTE CONF
more complex systems by which roaming assets, assets that roam
around the world, data that sits on your phone or
NOTE CONF
your laptop, blah blah, it sits outside the organization's premise,
that has to be controlled.
NOTE CONF
And we do that by creating layers around the asset
and keeping those layers moving with the asset.
NOTE CONF
That's still defense in depth is just not as sophisticated
as we used to have.
NOTE CONF
So things like multi-factor authentication and behavioral analytics allows us
to to move from pure boundary, where you cross the
NOTE CONF
boundary, now you can do anything to identity, which is
even if you've crossed a boundary, we're still going to
NOTE CONF
keep checking who you are.
Zero trust and moving from reactive to predictive rather than
NOTE CONF
looking at signatures of behavior, we can predict what bad
things will happen by using AI and we're moving from
NOTE CONF
on-prem to cloud, so we don't control the environment, but
we certainly still do have the ability to enforce rules
NOTE CONF
in other people's environment.
Right, that's where we're moving.
NOTE CONF
But again, bottom line in terms of technology controls.
The strategy is defense in depth.
NOTE CONF
So on the exam, for instance, if we ask you,
here's an organization, here are the assets that they have,
NOTE CONF
and we want you to design a defense in depth
strategy to protect this organization from this kind of actor.
NOTE CONF
First of all, you have to know what we mean
by defense in depth.
NOTE CONF
If you turn up to the exam and you don't
know what defense in depth is, you won't know that
NOTE CONF
you've got to look at all, a whole range of
controls and figure out how to stack them together to
NOTE CONF
create an environment that's challenging for the actor.
You need to know that.
NOTE CONF
Then you need to know what are the controls, and
then you need to explain to us how those controls
NOTE CONF
will work together, mostly managerial controls because we're not that
interested in the technological side, but certainly technological controls insofar
NOTE CONF
as you can say, we need to separate these assets
from these from these people, and we might enforce that
NOTE CONF
using firewall technologies or these sorts of technologies, right?
That's the kind of answer that we would expect on
NOTE CONF
the exam.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Good luck with your presentations, uh, and I'll see you
next week.
NOTE CONF
Sorry, one sec, 1 sec, it's gonna get recorded.
So OK.
NOTE CONF
And.
I'll see you later.
NOTE CONF
I have sure doesn't really affect it.
And then on, I have a question because I had
NOTE CONF
an last semester I had an assignment similar to this
and we came in a dilemma about putting our health
NOTE CONF
day by putting it on the file.
Something that we need to coordinate to sort of decide
NOTE CONF
the pros and cons.
So in reality when people decide to put their names
NOTE CONF
on the clouds.
What was their approach in the sense that is this
NOTE CONF
affected by Or it's, it's trust you're, you're trusting the
vendor you can have a contract and say blah blah.
NOTE CONF
Is there any way to check whether the contract to
be enforced?
NOTE CONF
Well, I mean.
That's the problem, right, is that you can have a
NOTE CONF
contract.
You can have a service level agreement with the, with
NOTE CONF
the guy.
Some companies create like a.
NOTE CONF
Where they have like a serial service now it's, right?
It's like a ticketing mechanism.
NOTE CONF
They create a ticketing mechanism.
They try to they try to get all the people
NOTE CONF
who are working on the vendor side to be transparent
about what they're doing so they can see.
NOTE CONF
Thank you.
Hi, um, so I was part of computing before switching
NOTE CONF
to cyber.
So, uh, all tutorials were full and I was going
NOTE CONF
for the 5 p.m. Thursday, and then the TAFF assigned
me at 1 p.m. So I'm still, I, I was
NOTE CONF
attending.
Yeah, but I'm still not part of any group.
NOTE CONF
So is it OK if I do it alone, or
like, I, yeah, but I'm still not part of any
NOTE CONF
group.
I started, uh, I had to switch subjects, so I,
NOTE CONF
I, um, I had to drop a subject, so it
was like the, it was clashing because normally.
NOTE CONF
I'm part of the subject.
No, no.
NOTE CONF
When did you enter and Who authorized it?
Did I authorize it?
NOTE CONF
Uh, yeah, no, I, I'm, I've started from like week
one.
NOTE CONF
You came in week one, yeah, yeah, but the class
assigned me, uh, the one.
NOTE CONF
No, it doesn't matter what they assigned you because I,
you can go to any tutorial.
NOTE CONF
You just have to tell me.
Oh yeah, in the beginning when they assign it, that's
NOTE CONF
just to try to get people into the classes once
they.
NOTE CONF
Do that ignore it, right?
I was going for 5, but now I want to
NOTE CONF
go for 1 because you're not in a group yet.
You've not done any work.
NOTE CONF
No, I can do the work.
No, no, you haven't done any work in a group
NOTE CONF
yet, yeah, OK, yeah, that's a bubble.
You're not going to pass.
NOTE CONF
I, I, I can do it, but, like, no, you
have to be part of a group and you have
NOTE CONF
to tell us if you weren't part of a group,
because if you're still not part of a group, you're
NOTE CONF
not gonna pass this assessment because it is a group
assessment.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, I, I can join a group and there is
still time.
NOTE CONF
If you join the group now, you're going to be
downgraded.
NOTE CONF
Seriously downgraded, right, because up until now you're almost done.
Every group has to be ready by Tuesday 1 p.m.
NOTE CONF
Everything has to be done by now.
So if somebody starts now, Tuesday 1:00 p.m. and tries
NOTE CONF
to contribute to a group.
We're going to downgrade that student massively because they can't
NOTE CONF
be the same as somebody who started when the assessment
started.
NOTE CONF
It would be unfair.
Yeah, but the teacher also changed for the 5 p.m.
NOTE CONF
and it doesn't matter.
You have to tell me.
NOTE CONF
I'm not in a group.
I also dropped an email to me, yeah, yeah, yeah.
NOTE CONF
I did see anything.
Did I respond to your email?
NOTE CONF
No, then I didn't get it.
I, I did.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, anyway, you have to, anyway, yeah, you've got to
do something.
NOTE CONF
I don't know where you'll, I'll do it alone.
It's totally fine.
NOTE CONF
I can assess you.
It's a group assessment.
NOTE CONF
Then everybody will want to do it alone because it's
easier.
NOTE CONF
How, how can I be part of a group if
I'm going to different?
NOTE CONF
I don't know.
Nobody else has to shoot, so send me another email.
NOTE CONF
I'll have a chat with the tutors, but I can't,
I can't guarantee you're going to pass it, right?
NOTE CONF
You have to have to be part of a group.
Sorry, we have to leave.
NOTE CONF
I think somebody else coming in.
You I'll probably come in.
NOTE CONF
Open this one up and then we can put.
I You should know that.
NOTE CONF
Maybe it's better having the food over there, yeah, so
then it's all.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
So.
NOTE CONF
Perfect.
Are they on their way?
NOTE CONF
Research cheap.
OK.
NOTE CONF
OK, you know that.
We're the same people.
NOTE CONF
I'm skip it for the design maybe.
Yeah, yeah.
NOTE CONF
Good, it's.
because Yeah.
NOTE CONF
Uh Great that Last week yeah.
Why?
NOTE CONF
special